Guide to the Marion Barry 1978 campaign oral history project collection, 1975-2018 MS2342
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Marion Barry 1978 campaign oral history project
1975 - 2017
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Tucker, Sterling
Coleman, Milton, 1946-
MS2342
91 item(s) 45 interviews, 45 transcripts, 1 pdf Digital files
1 Linear Feet Paper and artifact records
This collection contains oral histories (both audio and video recordings) of people associated with the Marion Barry campaign for mayor in 1978. The colletion also contains a small amount of paper records and artifacts related to the campaign and District government. These oral histories were conducted between 2015 and 2017. The collection as a whole dates from 1975 - 2017.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains oral histories (both audio and video recordings) of people associated with the Marion Barry campaign for mayor in 1978. The oral histories were conducted between 2015 - 2017. The collection also contains reports, t-shirts, buttons, publications and photographs associated with D.C. political history and the Barry campaign. These paper and artifact materials date from 1975 - 1985.
Historical note
In 1978 DC voters went to the polls to elect the second Mayor of the District of Columbia after the city was granted Home Rule in 1974. Marion Barry, an at-large member of the DC Council, ran against incumbent Mayor Walter Washington and Sterling Tucker, the DC Council Chairperson.
Barry was widely considered to be a maverick and a "street dude". He had abandoned his university doctoral program in chemistry in order to become a leader in the civil rights movement. He came to DC in 1965 to establish a chapter of the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee and quickly became prominent in local affairs. He founded Pride, Inc., an organization to train and employ young people. In 1971, he was elected to the DC Board of Education and became President of the Board. In 1974, Barry won an at-large seat in the first Home Rule City Council and was reelected to that seat two years later.
In the 1978 race, all the professional polls showed that Barry had zero chance of becoming Mayor, but he did. His election was a transformational moment in the political history of the District. Barry wooed and attracted dedicated and energetic political and community leaders who wanted a more progressive government; they viewed the campaign as a crusade for the soul of the city. A brilliant strategy was implemented by Barry's campaign manager Ivanhoe Donaldson. The Washington Post not only endorsed Barry but published follow-up editorials arguing for his election. And critical to the campaign's success, the Barry campaign registered large numbers of new voters and motivated others who rarely voted to come out for him. In a city dominated by the Democratic Party, the real contest occurred in the September Primary. The three candidates for mayor split the vote, with Barry receiving just a few thousand votes more than his competitors. He went on to win the General Election by a large margin. He was Mayor for three terms from 1979 until 1991 and was elected to a fourth four-year term in 1994.
In 2014, a couple of veterans of the 1978 Barry Campaign were reminiscing about that extraordinary summer and the enduring friendships that were forged among Barry's supporters. We decided that an oral history needed to be recorded before any more of us died, or as we euphemistically phrased it, "went to the great polling booth in the sky"! We recruited others to help us do the interviews, were delighted that the Gelman Library was eager to house our work and raised some funds for expenses.
Written by Betty King, 2015 December
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Recordings, Paper records and artifacts, and WTOP program "The Making of Marion Barry"
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Betty King, Kwame Holman, Diane Lewis, Gladys Mack, and Richard Maulsby, August - October 2015 (2015.036). Additional recordings have been donated as the project has continued.
See the Immediate source of acqusition note for Series 2 for the paper and artifact records donated.
Series 3 was a gift of WTOP 2019 August (Accession 2019.071)
Oral history -- Washington(D.C.); Washington (D.C.) Politics and government; Oral history; Political campaigns; City council members -- Washington (D.C.); Mayors--United States; Elections -- Washington (D.C.); Barry, Marion; District of Columbia. City Council.; Coleman, Milton, 1946-
- Interviews, 2015-2017; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains recorded oral histories and transcripts. These oral histories were conducted between 2015-2017. The participants in the project are all people associated with Marion Barry's mayoral campaign in 1978.
  - Allem, Johnny, 2017 September 21; Series 1
    Biographical / Historical
    Johnny Allem has been a journalist, political consultant, and activist, a businessman and writer. He moved to DC in 1969 and became involved in local politics and the campaign for Home Rule, while managing and consulting on Congressional and gubernatorial campaigns. He is founder and president of Aquila Recovery Clinics, modern, science-focused outpatient clinics in DC at Friendship Heights and Capitol Hill. His new book Say the Second Thing… focuses on actions useful in early recovery from addiction illness.
  - Barry, Cora Masters, 2016 August 13; Series 1
    Cora Masters Barry was a Professor of Political Science at the University of the District of Columbia in 1978. She worked for and supported Marion Barry in every one of his political campaigns. Mayor Barry appointed her as Chairwoman of the DC Boxing and Wrestling Commission, the first woman to hold such a position in the US. In 1993 she married Marion Barry. She founded the Recreation Wish List in 1994 and in 2001 opened the highly successful Southeast Tennis and Learning Center.
  - Berg, Lisa, 2018 September 22; Series 1
    Lisa Berg was the official photographer for Marion Barry's 1979 mayoral campaign. At the time of this interview, she was a successful professional photographer living in New York City.
  - Bennett, Loraine, 2015 August 28; Series 1
    Loraine Bennett was Ward 6 Coordinator in the 1978 and 1982 Barry campaigns. In 1979, she was appointed to the DC Human Rights Commission. Between 1983 and 1991 she served in the Mayor's Office of Constituent Services and later as Special Assistant in the Office of the Deputy Mayor for Economic Development. In 1991, she received the Mayor's Distinguished Public Service Award. She was a private consultant on community development until she returned to DC government as a manager in the Department of Consumer and Regulatory Affairs in 1999. She retired in 2005.
  - Berry, Max, 2015 October 21; Series 1
    Max Berry was the Chairman of the Finance Committee for Marion Barry's 1978 campaign. He has been a power in DC politics as a strategist and fund raiser since the 1960. Max is an international attorney in private practice. He and his wife, Heidi, were notable art collectors and were responsible together with Ann Kinney for recruiting prominent DC artists such as Sam Gilliam and Lou Stovall to contribute prints to sell for the campaign.
  - Beveridge, Albert, 2015 October 23; Series 1
    Albert Beveridge is a partner in the law firm of Beveridge & Diamond. Before Marion Barry could run for election as Mayor in 1978, he had to challenge as unconstitutional a provision of the DC Election Act that barred an elected office holder from running for another office unless the office he held expired on or before the date on which he would assume his new office or he resigned from his current office – a so-called "resign to run" law. Barry had two years left in his term on the City Council. Beveridge and his colleague, Andrew Mishkin, argued the case successfully (448 F. Supp. 1249 (1978), enabling Barry to run for Mayor. Mayor Barry appointed Beveridge to be Chairman of the DC Board of Elections and Ethics. In that role he led the challenging and contentious process of correcting the DC voting rolls and rectifying the many problems facing the Board.
  - Bonds, Anita, 2016 May - 2018 July 19; Series 1
    Anita Bonds has spent her entire adult life as a grassroots organizer, activist, and trusted political ally for campaigns and causes across the spectrum of the civil rights, social justice, worker's, LGBT, and women's equality movements. Anita is the current Chairman of the DC Democratic Party and serves on the Executive Board of the Democratic National Committee. Anita is a former Chairperson of the Ward 5 Democrats.
    Anita is a resident of Ward 5, an active member of Foundry United Methodist Church, a mother to three, and a grandmother.
  - Coleman, Milton, 2016 July 28; Series 1
    Milton Coleman was a reporter and editor at the Washington Post from 1976 until 2012. He covered DC politics and government from 1976-1980 and served as city editor from 1980-1983 and metropolitan editor from 1986-1996. At the time of the 1978 District mayoral elections, he was the chief city hall reporter for the Post and lived in Ward 7. He retired from The Post in 2012 as Senior Editor. He currently is the ombudsman for the Corporation for Public Broadcasting.
  - Cox, Courtland, 2015 August 20; Series 1
    Courtland Cox was active in the Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee [SNCC] while a student at Howard University in DC. He knew Marion Barry who had been the first President of SNCC and was living in DC. Cox helped with the 1978 campaign and entered the first Barry administration as Director of the Minority Business Opportunity Commission.
  - Donaldson, Ivanhoe, Series 1
    Ivanhoe Donaldson was the campaign manager of Marion Barry's 1978 mayoral campaign. He began this brief interview before his final illness made it impossible for him to complete it. Ivanhoe died in the spring of 2016.
    Related Materials
    Bruce Johnson from WUSA channel 9 interview Ivanhoe Donaldson on April 4, 2016. Here is a link the station has made availble on their website for that interview. https://www.wusa9.com/article/home/ivanhoe-donaldson-dead-at-74/119730385
    If the link does not work patrons should contact the TV station to inquire about availability.
  - Fleming, Virginia, 2015 May 20
    Ginna Fleming was working as a consultant on school desegregation and child health when she was asked to join Marion Barry's Transition Committee in 1978. Before home rule, the District had been governed by a Commissioner with oversight of a collection of unrelated offices in federal departments and various agencies, boards and commissions. Ginna's job was to help Barry and his advisors develop a table of organization that would bring a more functional municipal governance out of this previous informal pattern. In 1979 she became Executive Assistant to the City Administrator. She later held several other positions, including Deputy in the Planning Office, Director of the Mental Health System Reorganization Office and Deputy Director of the Department of Human Services.
  - Graves, Warren, 2017 August 21; Series 1
    Warren Graves worked on Walter Washington's successful campaign for Mayor of DC in 1974 and then became an assistant to the Mayor. When Marion Barry unseated Mayor Washington in 1978, he invited Warren to remain on his staff. Warren served in various capacities in all four of Barry administrations and continued in senior positions in the administrations of mayors Kelly, Williams, Fenty and Gray.
  - Gutierrez, Jose, 2016 April 29; Series 1
    Jose Gutierrez had 30 years of public service in the District of Columbia and federal governments. He served in several positions in Mayor Barry's cabinet, including Director of Human Resources, Chief Procurement Officer and Director of Administrative Services. He retired from federal service in 2006 and advises non-profit organizations on real estate developments.
  - Hammond, Sybil M., 2015 August 22; Series 1
    Sybil Hammond was Scheduler in the 1978 Barry Campaign and then served in the Mayor's Office as Appointments Secretary and later as liaison to civic organizations and constituent groups. From 1984-8, she was Director of the Office of Constituent Service and later was Assistant Supervisor of the Office of Banking and Financial Institutions, where she worked to ensure compliance with the federal Community Reinvestment Act. Sybil retired from DC government in 2015 as a senior official in the Department of Public Works.
  - Holman, Kwame, 2015 October 15; Series 1
    Kwame Holman was Marion Barry's driver during much of the 1978 campaign, accompanying him to campaign events in every part of the District. He was Deputy Press Secretary in the Mayor's Office in the first Barry administration. Later, he went to Northwestern University for a graduate degree in journalism. He was Political and Congressional Correspondent for The NewsHour on the Public Broadcasting System for 31 years.
  - King, Betty, 2015 September 13; Series 1
    Betty King was coordinator of special events fundraising in the 1978 Barry campaign. She served as the Mayor's Special Assistant for Boards and Commissions from 1979 until early 1990. In 1994 she chaired the mayoral campaign of John Ray. When Barry defeated Ray in the primary, she volunteered as deputy director of the transition to Barry's fourth administration. She returned to government and served as his deputy chief of staff and as ombudsman handling constituent services until she retired in 1997.
  - Knowles, Edna Lucille, 2015 August 20; Series 1
    Lucille Knowles volunteered as an Assistant Scheduler in Barry's 1978 campaign and served in the first Barry Administration as one of his Appointment Secretaries. She was Mayor Barry's Executive Assistant in the second campaign, after which she was Staff Assistant in the Office of Boards and Commissions. Upon the retirement of Betty King, she became the Special Assistant to the Mayor for Boards and Commissions. She retired from D.C. Government in 2001.
  - Kuntzler, Paul, 2015 August 22; Series 1
    Paul Kuntzler was one of the founders of the Gertrude Stein Democratic Club, the preeminent LBGT political organization in DC, and of a number of other LBGT organizations. He was a Barry supporter in the 1978 campaign, who early forecast Barry's victory. Mayor Barry appointed him to membership on the DC Lottery and games Control Board, on which he served for seven years. He was employed by the National Science Techers Association until his retirement in 2005.
  - Lee, Ethel Delaney, 2017 July 28; Series 1
    Ethel Delaney Lee came to Washington in 1952. She became a leader in her Ward 4 community and the Metropolitan African Methodist Episcopal Church and supported Mayor Walter Washington in the first home rule election in 1974. Then she met Marion Barry in 1978. That year she worked full time at the campaign headquarters and she supported Marion throughout the remainder of his political career.
  - Lewis, Delano E., 2015 August 13; Series 1
    Del Lewis came to DC in the 1960s to work in the Justice Department. Later he went to Africa with the Peace Corps. In 1971, he began working for DC Delegate to Congress Walter Fauntroy. He joined C & P Telephone Company (now Verizon) in 1973 as Public Affairs Manager and in 1974 he ran for an at large seat on the DC City, but lost. He supported Barry's campaign for Mayor in 1978 and was head of the Transition Committee after his election. Del worked for C & P for 21 years, after which he was President and CEO of National Public Radio and later served as US Ambassador to the Republic of South Africa.
  - Lewis, Diane, 2016 July 25; Series 1
    Diane Lewis is Co-Principal and Executive Vice President of ALTA Consulting Group, Inc., Washington, D.C., a management consulting firm, with extensive experience in health care policy, and community development.
    Ms. Lewis' professional experience spans over 35 years of work in government and the private sector as an employee, and entrepreneur. Ms. Lewis has worked to extend the reach and effectiveness of health systems in underserved/under resourced communities. Ms. Lewis directs collaborative efforts to improve the effectiveness of health systems and has worked with the non-profit community and foundations to expand health care access and women's health, develop workforce development strategies, advocate for and inform public policy.
    Ms. Lewis is currently, Chair of the Board, DC Health Benefit Exchange Authority (DC HBX). DC HBX serves as the health insurance marketplace where residents and small businesses have access to comprehensive, affordable health insurance. Ms. Lewis is also on the Board of the HSC Foundation, National Youth Transition Center – a collaborative learning community to benefit youth with disabilities and returning veterans.
    Ms. Lewis is a graduate of the City College of New York (B.A. Economics) and the Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs, Princeton University (MPA).
  - Long, Stuart, 2015 October 9; Series 1
    Stu Long is an attorney and restaurateur, who established the iconic Capitol Hill restaurant The Hawk 'n' Dove. He was a close personal friend of Marion Barry, supported him in all his political campaigns and raised money for them. Mayor Barry appointed him to serve as the chairman of the DC Armory Board.
  - Mack, Gladys, 2015 August 21; Series 1
    Gladys Mack was employed by Mayor Walter Washington as Deputy Budget Director in 1978 and so could play no role in the mayoral election. Her husband, Julius, was a strong Barry supporter. Gladys was one of Mayor Barry's first cabinet appointments as Assistant City Administrator for Budget. She served Mayor Barry for 12 years in a variety of senior positions. She went on to serve as Director of the United Planning Organization for 16 years. In 2003, she was appointed to the DC Hall of Fame for Community Service.
  - Mathis, Patricia, 2017 January 21; Series 1
    Patricia Mathis is Executive Chair and Founder of XCastLabs, Inc. and a trustee of the Episcopal Divinity School at Union Theological Seminary. She has been a thought leader in the communications space since divestiture. She is a former Assistant Secretary of the Treasury and has been appointed by several Democratic Presidents to lead national task forces. She was appointed by Mayor Barry to several boards and served with great distinction as a Trustee of the University of the District of Columbia.
  - Maulsby, Richard, 2015 August 22; Series 1
    Richard Maulsby was the founding President of the Gertrude Stein Democratic Club and coordinated the key role that gay organization played in the 1978 Barry campaign. He served as Director of the Office of Motion Picture and Television Development in the Barry Administration from 1979-1984 and held a cabinet position as Director of the Office of Cable Television from 1984-1991. He went on to work at the US Patent and Trademark Office until he retired.
  - McGrath, Kay, 2015 November 23; Series 1
    Kay McGrath was active in community and political affairs in DC for many years. In the 1978 campaign, she was part of a unit that wrote position papers and advised Barry on issues. After the election, she worked on planning issues in the office of the Deputy Mayor for Economic Development. Later she served in the Mayor's office doing community relations and ultimately went to the Police Department where she did liaison with the business community.
  - Meehan, Susan, 2015 August 27; Series 1
    Susan Meehan met Marion Barry when they served on the Pilot District Project, a pre-Home Rule program to improve police-community relations. She supported him in all his election campaigns and in 1978 was his coordinator for Ward Two. In 1979, she had a contract to assist in developing the DC government mechanism for responding to citizen complaints. Later she worked in the Office of Constituent Services as Ward 2 representative, before becoming the Patient's Advocate in the Department of Human Service for clients in Drug and Alcohol Abuse Treatment.
  - Meyers, Edward, 2015 September 22; Series 1
    Ed Meyers joined Marion Barry's staff at the beginning of home rule in January 1975 as Staff Director of the DC Council Committee on Finance and Revenue which Barry chaired, and later was Barry's chief of staff on the Council. In Mayor Barry's administrations, he served in such jobs as Deputy Director of Finance and Revenue, Director of Policy, Director of Communications and deputy to DC's Anti-Drug Czar, Sterling Tucker. Ed served under three mayors as a member of the DC Public Service Commission.
  - Nixon, Norman, 2015 August 30; Series 1
    Norm Nixon was one of a group of young people who worked on Marion Barry's 1978 mayoral campaign. In 1979 he graduated from Cardozo High School and in 1980 he was selected for the first Mayor's Youth Leadership Institute. Like many alumni of that program, he credits Mayor Barry and the Institute for opening undreamt-of opportunities for him. He had a distinguished career in DC government, largely in Employment Services, has been involved in many civic and community activities and has received numerous awards. He is an Associate Minister at Union Temple Baptist Church and works for the first adult public charter school east of the Anacostia River.
  - Oglivie, Lucie, 2018 September 25; Series 1
    Lucie Ogilvie was interviewed about her late husband, Dr. Phil Ogilvie, who was an important part of the campaign staff of Marion Barry's 1978 campaign. Before coming to Washington, Phil was a zoo director in Oklahoma City, Portland Oregon and Toronto. He served in the Barry administration, establishing the DC archives. He also researched and wrote extensively on DC history.
  - Page, Thornell, 2015 September 22; Series 1
    Thornell Page was an advisor to Marion Barry and supported him in all his campaigns. He was Director of the Extension Service at the University of the District of Columbia, and by choice never served in the Mayor's office. He later went on to other jobs, including being Assistant Director of Community Services in the administration of President Clinton. He is now President of Page Research Associates, Inc.
  - Passett, Barry and Margery, 2015 September 30; Series 1
    Margery and Barry Passett were leaders and Democratic activists in Ward 3. Margery organized the ward for Marion Barry's 1978 campaign. The next year she went to work for the then Hogan and Hartson law firm as a Legislative Specialist predominantly working on international trade matters. Barry participated in Barry's campaigns for Board of Educations and City Council and was Margery's assistant in the 1978 campaign. In 1979 he became President of the Greater Southeast Health Care System, providing medical services to the people of Ward 8. In that role, he was closely tied to the Barry Administration for the duration of the 1980s.
  - Patton, Douglas, 2016 June 28; Series 1
    Doug is an attorney and political consultant. He first met Marin Barry in 1968 at the Poor People's March in Washington. In 1971 they met again when Doug was managing Walter Fauntroy's campaign for Congress. Doug supported Barry in all his campaigns. When he became Mayor in 1979, Barry appointed Doug to the Board of Zoning Adjustment (1980-5) and the Lottery Board (1989). From 1976-1995, Doug was an ex-officio member of the Federal Election Commission. In 2016, he published his political memoir entitled The White Guy in the Room.
  - Raskin, Jamie, 2016 September 09; Series 1